This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the ITE
computer society and by it e software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Welcome to software engineering radio.
I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my
guest is Yens Goodstead. Yens is a
senior scientist at the French National
Institute for Computer Science and
Control, deputy director of the IQ lab,
former co-editor of the ISO C standard,
and author of Modern C all additions.
Yes, welcome to software engineering
radio. Is there anything I missed in
your bio that you'd like to add?
Hello. No, that's great. That's perfect
about it.
Thank you. So the goals for the listener
today for our show is to understand
what's happened in the sea world since
we last spoke if you can believe it 5
years ago now back in 2020 when your
book second edition came out. We're
going to understand how the latest C
standard is going and what to expect if
there's anything coming up. To explore
the latest changes in your modern Cbook
and how they apply to the reader.
explore your C transition header to help
people get set up on C23 if they're not
there already given it's 2025 and you
talk about a new comprehensive approach
for program failure I'd like to explore
if we have time so let's get started so
what if you can recall has happened in
the past 5 years in the C world and bear
in mind what happens in other
programming languages in five years has
a lot happened to C or not a lot
compared to say Rust or JavaScript or
how would you describe what's gone on?
First of all, you have to know that C is
really slow. So maybe that's the reason
also why we talked 5 years ago and not
every year or something like that. So
development goes slowly and we really
only standardize things that are already
implemented. So there's a long cycle for
new features to come in before you even
see them. So compared to other languages
for example which I most know the most
C++ they have a lot of more excitement
and fuzz and things going on and do
things and then they do them back and
then they do another thing and then they
do something which is not consistent. So
we try not to do that. We try to have a
steady pace slow but steady to go
forward. One of the things which were
outside of the C standard was another
say standard a technical specification
which talks about pointer provenence. So
this helps for those who know what that
is to deal with the pointers and objects
and things like that. And this is work
for took us 10 years something like that
and was mainly led by Peter Suril from
the University of Cambridge. So this was
a big effort which now is concentrated
in one technical specification which in
some years perhaps might go into the C
standard. So this is really what one of
the things that went on in addition to
the C standard itself for the moment.
I'll get that link from you in the show
notes.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I'll give you a
link on that so we can share that. There
had been a lot of discussions also about
the security of C code compared to other
languages. I was not always happy with
these kind of discussions because my
main impression always has been there
have been some major misunderstandings
what C is and what C can do and what C
wants to do and what other languages
make different and what cost benefit
ratio is. C is a relatively specialized
language where you can do many many
things. So all security buttons are
somehow off and this is by design and
that's not an accident. So if you don't
want that you probably are programming
in the wrong language in some sense.
Did the work on the pointer and object
alses help with the security side of
things or
on the long run we hope that this will
help. Yes, but this has to be integrated
in compilers yet or stated a little bit
differently. the compiler vendors really
have to check if they are confirming to
that model. So basically everybody is
convinced that this is right model that
basically everybody should be there and
have that but there's so many details to
check for the compiler producers that
they wanted it to be a technical
specification so they already have
something written up but they have to
check that over the next years implement
stuff which is perhaps missing and
things like
would it be practical to sort of explain
an example of these aliases? and how
they help with security.
The main issue which is in the title is
provenence. So provenence we define of a
pointer is somehow to which object in a
wider sense this pointer is pointing. So
every allocation say if you call me malo
or kelloc or something like that or if
you have a declaration of a variable
gives rise to a different provenence and
if two pointers point to two different
such things which were allocated at
different times the compiler can know
that they are really different because
they come from something very far apart
and this can help by doing a singing
light analysis and than being able to
optimize because the compiler can prove
that two pointers actually point to
different things. So this is basically
the idea behind this and then getting
this through all levels of the language
and all levels of the compilers and
everything. So this is quite technical
then in the details.
So this would do away with dangling
pointers completely.
This will not do away with dangling
pointers by themselves. This will do
away with you have two parameters to the
same function which are pointers and
then the question is whether these can
point to the same thing and so the
compiler has to be careful or not
whether when you change one of these
things will change the other at the same
time. Okay, that sounds a lot like what
Rust enforces with borrow checking and
things like that and sort of garbage
collect memory languages might do where
they track every variable.
Yeah, this is related to these kind of
questions in C. Yeah, you only have
these things implicit and so it's
basically a compiler who is then able to
prove some things and this is where
things get technically really nasty. So
we needed a really good model and
there's some real formal specification
in the mathematical sense and that paper
was really difficult thing to do.
So we could get in a situation where
once you're using the an updated
compiler it could find all these bugs
for you cuz it's tracking everything at
that point. So one thing to note is also
in the last 5 years compilers have been
gotten really much much better than they
were 10 years ago or something like
that. So they're really able to track
things much easier down and to warn you
about stuff and things like that. So
there has been a real leap forward I
think in what compilers are capable of
at least the compilers I know best which
are these public domain compilers GCC
and clang they're
exciting times then
yeah it is we are in excited times yeah
so our latest standard is C23 and that's
what your book's been updated to cater
for and can you give us a pitch of what
it is C23
yeah so C23 is the first major edition
to C since C11. So 12 years. So you have
to have in mind at least the development
cycle for C has been so there has been
an intermediate standard which was
basically bug fixes in in 17 and so C23
is the first which has really new
features compared to C11. Among these
features are small ones and big ones.
There's really a lot I could point you.
For example, one of the things you
probably don't even notice is that we
reduce the possible sign representations
to two's complement. Before there had
been other possibilities and now in C we
restrict to two's complement. Everybody
uses tooth's complement anyhow. You
learn that in school and everything. But
now it's official since season 23 that
this is the only way to represent signs
for integers. We changed some spelling
of keywords. We added const x facility.
We added auto and type of off for type
inference. We added attributes which
gives you the possibility to annotate
constructs in the language in a
systematic way. Yeah, we'll be going
over some of those shortly in the next
section.
Yeah, we updated the uni code support.
So, identifiers in C now are really
ruled by uni code. What's possible to
have in an identifier? There are clear
uni code rules for that. And before we
had some homebrew tables of what was
possible and what not. And so we changed
to be conforming to this other standard.
We also added more facilities to the
standard C library to transform
different encodings. We added bit
fitting utilities. Everybody probably
knows how to do a pop count of so
counting the bits of an integer and
everybody probably does it wrong if they
only have half an hour to program this.
So this gives you a unique way to do
that with a function call and which is
then optimized by your implement for
your platform. What you have we have
checked integer arithmetic so you can
check for overflow and we have added con
safety for some library functions. So
it's just rough very rough overview.
Thank you. We'll we'll dig in a bit more
in the next section. So how does that
work? Say you you've just explained
there's a new function to help count the
bits in an integer.
Yeah.
So practically wise that would appear in
GIC C and other.
Yeah.
this appears or let's state it different
all the compilers already had it have it
with different names and so we are just
putting some glue on top of it which is
an unique name and GDPC then would
provide that in a header too so you can
so you'd get an updated version of GCC
which would come with the headers
yeah so you can use that uh portably
for different
and that function is then defined in the
GCC source code someone's written it.
Yes, for most of these function actually
they exist for example in GCC they exist
as buildins. So this will not even give
rise to a function call at the end. This
will be directly transformed into some
assembly by the compiler. This is
already built in with this prefixed
underscore underscorebuiltin something
behind. GCC has a lot of them. And what
the header of GIPC then only would do
would give you basically macro interface
which translates to this built-in of the
compiler
and the GCC team would have done all the
work inside.
Yeah. GCC team had done this most of the
work already before
and then to validate that they look up
the Cspec and make sure the inputs and
outputs match what the spec says.
Yeah. Exactly. Exactly. So this is the
bit of work they have to do because when
you standardize things like that
everybody has chosen a different name
for these kind of functions and so we
have to agree upon one name for a
specific function and then everybody has
to do some homework getting things right
uh with exactly the right name and right
order of parameters and things like
that. the stakeholders and all the
different compilers would be represented
in the C committee. Is that how
not all but some of them? Yeah.
Some of them. Yeah. And probably not for
this function but for other functions
with the internal implementation of
these functions will obviously be
different depending on what team has put
them into GCC or C lang or wherever.
Yes, even for these functions these
could be different because they might
depend a lot on the process that you
have. So the processor may an Intel
versus an RM may have different
primitives and so the goal for the
compiler team would be to match that to
the good primitive which makes this
quick and easy and so there are
certainly different choices to make for
the implementation for certain things
and what's only guaranteed by the
standard is the semantics of such a
call.
Yeah,
basically that it does the same thing.
Or would there be situations where your
project or program would be faster
compiling it? Not compile speed, but
actually runtime might be faster if it's
built with GCC or CM because of those
internal implementations.
Yes, sure. There always differences in
these things between the different
compilers.
And that's something that you have to
figure out, I suppose, when you do
benchmarking.
Yeah, if you do benchmarking, you can
figure this It's nice to think about how
it goes from standard to implementation
and actually getting in your hands and
how that could be different as well. And
if you're on the GC team or just the C
programmer in general, how do you
recommend people keep up to date with
not only what's just in the standard,
but do they just publish the standard
and we're all left to go and read it or
is there another source of information
that you can say these things would
benefit you or does it just trickle
downream until your compiler says
something? No, it's really a process of
compiler people adding things to their
compilers and because they have a
demand. So usually when there's new
feature there are people that like to
have that then compiler vendors
implement this and if a feature appears
in several compilers and the community
says oh yeah yeah this one is now
something that we think that is stable
then we are going to standardize that.
So this is really a feedback loop in
that sense.
Okay. So it's back to front.
The standardization often then is only
Yeah. giving a a unique name to that
function or something like that.
That makes sense because you're not just
going to make up stuff in a standard
just because you wanted something to do.
It's because you're
tendencies to do so also for certain
things. But for all what I said, at
least for the C library, this is usually
really the case that this comes from
somewhere and is then standardized.
Okay, thank you. So is there going to be
such a thing as C26 or is it going to be
C34
or how do you think that will pan out?
Yeah, so there will be no C26.
Okay,
we are working on C2Y. So C26 would not
exist. C2Y where Y is not yet fixed is
in the works. So there are already a lot
of papers accepted for that. There's a
intermediate version of the standard
where the editor has already integrated
most of these changes but this will
certainly take us at least 2 or 3 years
still. So this might be 28 29 something
like that. That's pretty good though cuz
the last one C23 that's another seven
six years for the next
yeah so 6 years would be our usual
schedule let's say like that by
experience but this time this will not
be just an fix release this time this
will be a real feature release also
okay the one before was C1 so it's quite
fast
there was C C17 in between which was
this bug fix release
okay yeah and is there any major you
said There's new features in C2Y.
Yeah, there's some new features which
for example one thing we get from C++
actually this is definition of variables
inside if and switch statements. I don't
know if you know about that feature. In
the expression part of an if and C++ you
can first declare a variable and then
evaluate that variable. For example, if
you're making a system call, you can
assign the result of the system call to
a temporary variable for which only
lives inside the if statement and then
check for the value of that.
Yeah. Recently I've been doing mainly
Rust programming and that's something
you do in Rust quite often.
Yeah. Yeah. So this kind of neat feature
which is not very difficult to
implement. We have added things to the
pre-processor. For example, we now have
the counter feature. So you have the
underscore underscore counter
which gives you at each time which it's
evaluated in the prep-processor a new
number. So you can do that for saying
uniquely naming some variables which are
produced by macros or something like
that. We have removed imaginary types.
So before there was a concept of
imaginary type which nobody implemented.
Was this one of the things that appeared
in the spec first and then didn't
appear? Ah yeah so there was at one
point in history there was one
implementation for that but the way
complex numbers were described were
basically described as being reals and
then plus this imaginary part and how
this imaginary part which is then
imaginary in both sense of the terms
would look like and this complicated the
write up of the standard a lot and made
it really difficult to read at some
points. And so we decided that we get
rid of that and removed all that from
the standard and have just complex
numbers. We have added complex literals
which didn't exist surprisingly before.
So now if you just have a real number
with the suffix I then you get a complex
with this number as imaginary part.
things like that. And there are a lot of
things which are already voted in favor
but still need adjustment before they
can really be included. And so there's a
still a long way to go for this. There
we have a real large backlog of papers
which we can only treat so much in a
session that when we're meeting and so
the only thing I remember about
imaginary numbers is a university with
engineering just inj used to represent.
Uh yeah yeah yeah.
Yeah. So these things that are getting
changed what's the process for that? You
said they publish a paper you review it
as a board and then you chat about it or
I think we might have spoken about this
last time we spoke but in the next 2
years or C28 or 29 what goes on in those
years?
Yeah. So as I said basically for example
like this counter prep-processor feature
this is basically already implemented in
every compiler. So this exists so you
have to write a paper to already first
advertise that why you want that and
then you have to provide text how this
would be integrated into the standard
and then this goes usually over some
iterations with the committee. There's
discussion on the email list and then
there's discussion.
So is this like a working group type
thing debate on this?
There are working groups but most of the
things are done in C are done in
plenary. We are only about 30 people or
so which meet regularly.
So somebody writes a paper and publishes
it to that list for you all to consider.
Yeah
I see. Okay. I was just trying to figure
out where people find those papers but
it's all a proper process. There's a
website for the C committee where you
can find all these papers. You can
Okay, I'll get that off you later.
Yeah, we can put that in the links too
and you can see all revisions of all
papers and it's really long list.
Okay, I think we've covered our
introduction a bit more than that. So,
we might speed through the next section.
So, I've called this section the latest
C standard bracket C23 and upcoming
changes. So, I think we've touched the
upcoming changes quite a lot with C2Y,
which sounds really cool,
but let's pull apart some of the things
we just mentioned. So, I've got a few
bullet points here that I'll take you
through questions. So, why are these
improvements to integers and enums
needed that are in C23? And I've got a
quote here where you say in the updated
version of your book intro or the
marketing pitch for it, I think there
are new bit precise types coined
underscore bit int brackets capital N
and new C library headers standard CD
intHth H for arithmetic overflow checks
standard bith for bit manipulation
possibilities for 128 bit types of
modern architectures etc so immediately
I thought integers are integers what's
changed and why are these things needed
so could you give me some insight into
those
first of all integers are not integers
There are 15 different integer types,
standard different integer types and you
have a lot of problems with overflow
with conversion.
So if the conversion is narrowing or
widening and things like that. So
because we don't have a big int type as
other languages have, you always are
reduced to something some given
precision. Whatever that precision is,
what you choose, you really need to be
aware of that if you're going too far to
big numbers, then you have wrap around
or something like that or or stuff like
that. You have the problem of if you are
doing for example comparison between two
integers when one of these integers is
signed and the other is unsigned, what
should be the semantics of this
comparison be and so on. So this is not
completely trivial and see how to deal
with these and therefore we talked
already a little bit of this bit
manipulation
thing. So this offers new opportunities,
new interfaces.
So that would be the standard bit H
header.
Yeah, this is this stdbit age thing.
Standard checked integer gives you an
interface where you can check for
overflow. So you basically do arithmetic
say an addition between two integers and
these functions which are in this
interfa in this header they will not
only give you the result of that
addition but they will also give you a
flag back whether or not you had an
overflow in that addition or not. So you
can do checks, you can abort your
program if numbers are getting too large
or whatever you want to do and this goes
down the drain. So up until this was
standardized people would be doing this
anyway but just have created something
themselves.
Yeah. Again there were builtins for
compilers which did that. So this was
not portable not so easily portable or
people did their checks by themselves
and then with all the possibilities of
getting this wrong. So if you have time
and look up on stack overflow for
example there are questions of how to do
that you have a lot of answers and a lot
of them are wrong. So you have some
special cases which are covered and the
idea here really is to have that done on
one hand correctly which is already a
good thing and then also using as for
the bit manipulation part using already
the right assembly instruction for
example for that because most processors
already do that correctly. they have
this overflow bit and you you just have
to do the addition in the assembler and
then read the overflow bit whether or
not this worked or didn't work. So this
is much more efficient and much safer.
So this is basically the idea behind the
other thing which you also mentioned is
this thing with 128 bit types. The
problem has been that we had an actually
upper limit in the width of integers
which was is the type u inint max_t
which on most modern architectures was
64-bit
and on the other hand in many or there
are really applications where you really
like to have wider types for example for
cryptography or check some calculations
or things like that and the modern
processes all implement these 128 bit
arithmetic but there was no way to map
them correctly into the C library in the
C language because we had this
artificial restriction on how wide an
integer could be. So we this was a lot
of work of fiddling with the standard
text actually to allow that to happen
and now to offer the possibility to go
beyond these limits that we have.
And does the term wide integer is wide
the bit size?
Yeah. Wide is a bit size. Yeah.
Yeah. And do you get input from go back
to the standard from CPU companies that
say we now support this we should put
something in the standard or do they
release a tool set with the CPUers?
Yes and no. We have one big player which
is really invested also in the C
standard which is Intel but they are
mainly invested because of their
compilers. So they are really supporting
clang and they are really interested in
C from that perspective. We had this
underscorebit in record n types which
actually also came from Intel but for a
very different reason than one might
think. They had this because they wanted
to have such a type in FBJs and things
like that where you really want to be
able to design your integer type with
every bits such that you can lay out
your network of computing correctly in
this FPJI with exactly the resources
that you want.
Is that an FGPA?
I haven't heard that word since
university and I think it's field
programmable gate arrays. I was thinking
that's not what you said.
Yeah, but that's what I meant. So,
Oh, okay.
FPGAAS. Yeah, I remember doing that in
my degree.
Do you think these wider types are they
getting driven by machine learning type
stuff, AI type stuff or where's the need
for them coming from? Machine learn goes
actually in the inverse direction which
is not yet covered by the C standard.
The machine learning guide they want to
have floating point which is really
short. So for them float for example
with this 32 bits is already much too
large. They want to have floating points
sometimes with eight bits only or
something because they really want to do
approximate computations very very fast
and with really slow memory footprint
for everything etc to do more and more
and then they only need to do some steps
for the real position afterwards. So
they really have that and they're
currently and this is one of the main
reasons we haven't standardized that I
think for 8bit floating point there are
at least 10 different specifications by
different providers which are all
different in some aspect somewhere and
what the mantisa is or they present and
things. So this is probably something we
will see at some point to be
standardized but there's still a long
way to go because everybody now has
their own 8bit floating point somewhere
implemented and it's not compatible to
what the other guys are doing and so
it's not easy to standardize.
No, that's interesting. I thought maybe
it was like the vectors and things they
use and just to speed everything up.
No, it's more the crypto guys things
like that. So it's really interesting
for crypto to at least to have bit
operations on large recctors and this
works quite well for them.
Excellent. Okay. So I'll take us through
a couple of more bullet points but we've
still got a bit to cover cuz I want to
talk about additions to your book. So we
might move a bit quicker through these
ones. So what is a null pointer constant
in regards to the standard?
Yeah. So before we had null all in
capitals which is just a macro which was
somehow illdesigned or not well
specified. So this can underneath the
hood can be different things and this
led to potential problems for example
when you use that as an argument to
printer or something like that. So we
had this sitting there. We cannot easily
change things like that because it's
used by everybody. And so we invented
something new which hasn't this this
ambiguity which null all capital null
has. So we integrate that really into
the language and not into the macro
preprocessor.
All caps null macro. Has that remained
the same since was first created 50
years ago or so?
Yeah, basically. So all of a sudden in
the 20s they decided no we need
something else. It's never come up
before.
It has come up before. So C++ had so
this null pointer comes from C++.
C++ has done this 12 years ago at least
I think in in C++ 11. I don't remember
exactly because they had exactly the
same problem because they inherited that
from us and they invented that and so we
just applied that same change to C.
Cool. And what are syntactic annotations
with attributes?
So perhaps people know this underscore
underscore attribute feature from GCC
and clang also implements that where you
can add properties to a function to a
parameter to a variable. You can
basically there are a lot of lot of
attributes like that which were
implemented before. The problem with the
approach that they had was that this was
syntactically not clear to which
construct an attribute applies. So you
put sometimes you put the attribute in
front of the function declaration
or behind the function declaration and
these different places had different
meanings and it was something yeah which
engineers do do. So somebody invented
something here and some money there and
then you had a lot of addup of these
kind of features and the attributes
which is also a C++ feature which we
adapted to C is now a syntax
annotation where it's unique to which
construct an attribute applies.
Basically big rule is just as for other
things it always applies to the left. So
if you put an attribute for example
behind after a function declaration
after the closing parenthesis and this
would apply to the function to the type
of the function. If you would put it
after the identifier it would only apply
to this specific identifier and things
like that. So you can annotate
things like that. There are some
standard attributes
for example something like deprecated.
You can mark an identifier as being dep
deprecated and so compiler will tell the
user who uses that at every compilation,
hey guy don't remember this one you
shouldn't use. And then there are a lot
of vendor specific attributes where
where compiler vendors have the
possibility to invent every thing stuff
they need they want to add to their
compilers for flow analysis or for
whatever feature they they want to have.
But it's clear by the syntax to which
structure of the program of this
applies. I've got four bullet points
coming up. I'm going to just say them
all out loud and then you can pick two
of your favorites because we need to
move on. I think about your book. Okay.
So, the first of the four is what is
generic programming with regards to type
inference with auto and type of off?
What is default initialization with
curly brackets? What are compound
expressions with lambdas? And what is
so-called internationalization?
So which of those two get you excited
the most that you'd like to talk about?
I won't talk about compound expressions
lambdas because they are not even in the
standard yet. And I won't talk about
internationalization because we already
talked about uni code and things like
that a little bit. So let's talk about
generic programming auto and type of off
and also initialization with brackets
which are both or all three auto and and
the brackets are features we all also
inherited from C++. So auto is a
possibility to keep your code
consistent. If you have a function which
depends on a parameter x and this has
some type and you don't remember that
type but you need another variable
auxiliary variable somewhere which
depends on that and which should have
the same type you just type auto y
equals x and then y gets exactly the
same type and value as x and then you
click continue.
Yeah, it's kind of like a dynamic
language then isn't it? This this just
helps you to stay consistent. So if
anybody changes X during development
then Y will change automatically with
it. And type of is a little bit more
complicated. It takes an expression or a
type as an argument and then deres the
type from that. This is used or useful
in in a lot of macro development or
things like that where you like to be
able to deduce types or automatically
from from what you get as macro
arguments. For example, before
initialization with braces closes say a
loop or whatever. Before initialization
in C, you always had to put at least one
initializer into into these braces. So
you had to say if you have an array A of
type double of size five, you would have
to put at least one zero into these
braces for initialization.
And the rest would then be before
initialized. And now you can just omit
everything and just put the braces. And
then by that saying that everybody every
member of your array is before
initialized. And this even works for
these so-called VA variable length
arrays. So even for arrays where you
don't know the length where it's
determined not at compile time but at at
runtime you can do that. So the compiler
will produce code that does this
initialization for you. You don't have
to do a for loop to initialize all your
array which you had to do before
to saves the programmer some time. Yeah.
And be ensure that it's consistent.
That's always these two aspects actually
that that you really have to be sure
that people don't do too much errors. So
So with these types of things, if you
switch to using them, would you feel
confident in using them or would you
need to create some tests to make sure
they're doing what they should be or how
do you advise people to get rid of code
basically delete stuff because it's now
done automatically somewhere? So first
of all again with these bracers
compilers implemented that since a long
time
okay because C++ also has that so it's
already there in the compilers it works
people use it and now this gives you the
official
stamp that this is how it's supposed to
be and you can change all your code to
that without any difficulties. So even
if you have to backport it to some
little bit older version of your
compiler, this should work.
Excellent. And you said compound
expressions and lambdas aren't really
standardized yet.
Yeah. Yeah. Unfortunately,
I put a lot of work in lambdas and it
was not taken for C23. I'm not sure that
we get something like that for TC to Y.
I am I'm not sure. People are very
divided on that. And then then it's
really difficult to make progress.
What's the use case for it in C?
The use case for
the lambdas and compound expressions in
C. Why do you want it?
Yeah, lambdas for they exist in many
languages. So for example in C++ are
very useful tool if you have callbacks
which you want to pass into a function.
And in C now the official way is always
to create outside of the function you
are currently writing. Before you have
to write this call back as a separate
function far away from where you're
going to use it and then you pass a
function pointer to that function as a
call back somewhere else in your code.
So you get get these things very far
apart and that that makes it difficult
to maintain and and everything. So
lambda would be some sort of short
function which you could actually put in
place where you pass it as a callback
and so everybody would see immediately
at that place. Here I'm doing call back
for I don't know what press button or
whatever and you see how that works and
where that is all in one place.
I suppose a lot of arguments against
these types of things is that your IDE
will help you find things.
Yeah, this is part of the argument. Then
there's part of more or less small
design questions on how to do that. How
to do that semantically, syntactically.
The question is if you have a lambda in
a certain place, what does this lambda
see from the surroundings? Is it
possible to access local variables for
example in the surroundings or not? Or
what would be the mechanism to integrate
them? And there people It's a little bit
exaggerated, but you sometimes you think
people would kill each other for for
these two these things.
Well, people are very passionate about
what they love.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Stately like that.
They are very passionate about things.
Yeah.
That's the nice way to say it. I suppose
we should talk about the bit that you're
most excited about and that's your book.
Yeah.
Modern C third edition. I can't believe
it. I've actually got the hard copy
posted to me a month or two ago when it
came out. Okay.
So, very excited to receive that. So,
yeah, let's do the chat about that now.
So, given what we've just spoken about
and we went quite deep and some new
things that I wasn't expecting to talk
about, which was great. What does the
latest edition of your book bring to the
SeaWorld? So, it has been completely
reworked for C23.
So, integrate all the shiny new features
from C23 if you scan. So it's difficult
on the hard copy. So you you would have
to go to the electronic copy. If you
search for mention of the string C23 in
it, you get about 200 mentions. So this
all over the place. And if you really
want to know what C-23 is, that's a
really good way to do you see it every
here and there. there is this little
thing which makes things easier where
you don't have to think about that where
you can do things easier with another
feature etc etc. So in that sense it's
really deeply integrated now into the
book that's really was also the the
motivation to do that.
It's also really good that the standards
are quite far apart in time so you get
to update a book to the latest standard.
It's not like every couple years. So
yeah. Yeah. Yeah. That's right. Is that
right? So the process of generating this
new edition was also quite lengthy. So
which I did in some parts in parallel to
what we did on the standard. Still it
took a lot of time to actually appear at
the end. So
how many pages did you add?
Oh, I don't know. I don't know. There's
some
I'll work it out. I've got both copies
here.
Yeah. Yeah. You
I'm a bit of a fanboy.
So it's thicker. It's thicker. That's
for sure. But I didn't do page counting.
You talk about one of the pictures in
your book that you've got an easy
transition header to get across to C23.
Yeah.
Can you take us through that a little
bit?
As I said previously, many of the
features already are there in compilers.
Only often there is a this is written
this has a little bit different name or
perhaps maybe even arguments are in
different order or things like that. So
what this header does, which you can
download with the examples from the
book, is to provide you already the
interfaces that match that on your
current perhaps not so updated compiler.
I only tested that for GCC and clang. So
I wouldn't know how this works uh really
works for other compilers. But let's say
that these are probably the major
compilers nowadays. So to give you an
example, there is a macro in C23 which
is called unreachable
and GCC and clang already have macros
built in unreachable. And so what my
header does is just matches this new
wording new name to the old ones. So
this is a little bit the way this works.
I'm not sure that you even would need
that nowadays. So I've written that what
two years ago or something. Now these
compilers have officially transitioned
to C23 already with their newest
version. So probably you won't even need
that. But if you still are stuck with a
clang from 2 years ago or 3 years ago or
something like that, you could use that.
Yeah. In the C world, that's not unheard
of, is it?
This is not unheard of. Exactly. But you
can use that and you be sure that you're
future proof for future changes. Once
do you know how many versions of C
standard the compilers keep around in
their own source code? You know if you
mark your code C11 or C89
C89 but
GCC still has all versions of C.
Wow. That's amazing isn't it?
And it's a lot of work to keep that
consistent. So yeah.
Wow. Cool. So, another thing that was
really exciting in your book was what
you've called a comprehensive approach
for program failure. That really piqu my
interest. Can you take us through that
if it's possible?
That's nice to hear because I put a lot
of brain effort into that. And one of
the reasons I started writing this up
was because I had the impression that
there were a lot of misconceptions about
what failure is in C or what a fault is
in C and things like that. So basically
I was categorizing
failures, program failures into four
main groups. The first one is
wrongdoings. So it's your fault when you
do something wrong. I don't know you
dreference a null pointer or you you do
whatever bad thing you can do in C. This
is basically the easy part where you
should whenever it's possible get a
diagnostic from your compiler or your
program should really fault very quickly
or something like that. Then there is
the next
layer of faults that lead to program
failure which are program state
degradation. So for example if you have
store ex exhaustion.
So this is generally something which you
can check if you check for example the
return of system calls. So if malo
really gives you a null back then you
know that something deeply went wrong
with your program. there's no storage
available anymore and so you really
should stop and do an emergency C exit
from your program or something like
that. So that was the second level. The
third level are unfortunate incidents.
Unfortunate incidents are things that
you don't really notice, you don't which
are difficult to track and things like
that. For example, like a race condition
in between two threads in a in a
threaded program. There are two entities
doing their things and two threads for
example and seen locally everybody's
doing the right thing but together they
don't work. This is something which you
can basically only avoid by really
careful design. So this false program
failures for unfortunate incidents
usually only appear when you have a bad
design. But what is a good and what a
bad design obviously is a really
difficult question. And then you have
the fourth thing which is a series of
unfortunate incidents where you are
basically caught in a bubble. You have
doing decisions on your own. You're
you're going around a block in a city
for example, at each corner you decide
because of something to go to the left
and if you do that consistently you will
always walk around the block and never
get out. So you're caught in some sort
of bubble because you're taking local
decisions decisions which don't lead you
which don't have you make progress at
some point. So this is also a really
difficult design question to answer. So
this is what failure is. But the problem
then is that you have to really
distinguish the error. So if you talk
about a sickness or something like that.
So this would be something which is
wrong or goes wrong from the way it
manifests from the symptoms. And this is
something which is often conflated by
people in C and generally in programming
languages I think. So so symptoms can be
compiler diagnostics, there can be
compilation failure, there can be
program termination or even worse there
can be real crashes. There can be
erratic behavior, silent misfunctioning.
All these different symptoms can appear
if you have a failing program. You
really have to navigate these and to
know why your program fails and what to
do against it to first of all try to do
some to work that it never happens or if
you can't avoid it then see how to
manage if it occurs and terminate your
program for example in a controlled way.
Okay, just to summarize those four
categories you created, you got what you
call user errors.
Yeah. Wrongdoings I call them. Yeah.
Yeah. Memory system issues.
Yeah. State degradation. So, memory
system issues. But this can be I don't
know file system full or things like
that. So, so
and then three would be unexpected
events.
Yeah.
And four would be a combo series of
those un
Yeah. combo series of those which make
you seem to do in progress but actually
you don't.
Yeah, that could be something like you
see in the news when AWS goes down or
something and something triggers
something else and it's not supposed to
spike that much and then that doesn't
feed back to that and it keeps going and
keeps going that type of issue.
Yeah.
Okay. How do we approach these four
things then? So the first is discipline
for one wrongdoings. Have a programming
style. Always keep to that programming
style. Listen to your compiler. If
they're telling you here's something
fishy, there is probably something fishy
and you should do that. What the
compiler suggests generally you should
against programs state generation. You
always should check return of system
calls. So every system call should
either be in an if statement or you
should take the the return value into a
variable and then decide whether or not
this was successful.
Does the standard or compiler help with
that type of thing?
Yeah. So so usually the C library for
example you have for all alt you have
return and you have you have specified
what happens when an error occurs and so
you can program against that. So
no but does the compiler enforce that
you check those?
There are possibilities that compilers
enforce to check these. Yeah.
Okay.
This is this is possible. So these are
the first two in that sense. This is
depends on the quality of your code
directly how you write it and that you
follow a style which is consistent in
itself and you have the right tools
compilers or analyzers or something
which give you hints on what to do. The
other two are much more difficult to to
handle. So they really need careful
algorithms designed. So for example,
race conditions between threads, you
really have to look and learn into and
there's a chapter in the in the book
about threads and atomics and mutexes
and all that stuff how you can avoid
that risk conditions occur from in the
first place. For example, for this force
for these unfortunate incidents, it's
much much more difficult because you
have basically to have proofs in your on
your algorithms that there is always
progress and this is not something which
is in general or whether general rules
or something how to do that. you have to
really have to do some thinking to
and you could probably apply those four
rules that you've created to any
language really any programming
I guess so yeah yeah probably you could
have that to for different languages
where you certainly have different kind
and this is probably something where
which could somehow rank languages
whether or not the first two points are
detected automatically or basically the
syntax ex inhibits that you're doing
certain types of faults or something. So
their C is probably
on the lower end. So you can probably
and we're trying to do that at some
point improve C and the diagnostic
that's that are given. For the last two,
there's basically all languages have
these problems and basically all
languages have the same amount of detail
or whatever which they can help you or
don't. How do you yourself when you're
creating this approach say for the thing
with uh threads example do you have a
set of example programs that you write
to to prove these things or work around
them or how do you translate this sort
of real world experience you've gained
into into your writing
for all threading for example and
problems like this I think the C
standard gives the right tools with
atomics and mutexes and things like
that. So you really only have to apply
them consequently and consistently to
get things right. I was just thinking
maybe you have your own C project that
you break things and fix things and
break things just to have a play and
compare.
Yeah. So what I'm currently working on
is having contracts for C which is
something like that to make some
guarantees about things automatically
which is I already published a paper for
that but which hasn't yet even been
discussed by the seat committee but this
would be a way to go forward to have
actually more tools in the language in
the syntax to guarantee certain things
and have automatic more or less
automatic proofs for certain things. So
this would be one direction to go but
this is early stage I'd say.
Well I think that's probably time up for
us. Is there anything in your book that
we've missed that you're really proud of
or even in not in the new edition that
you you want to highlight that you think
will make people's lives much better in
the sea world?
No, I think we covered it well. There's
so many things in the book. So, so you
really have to dig through it to learn
it.
So, obviously the C programming language
and standards and world is powering on.
But if there was one thing a software
engineer should remember from our show,
what would you like that to be?
I think the most important thing is to
stick to some sort of coding style or
something like that. Be consistent.
That's really the most important thing.
And listen to your compiler. That would
solve 50% of your four.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So basically compile
things without warnings and then Yeah.
And you're already quite good. So
yeah, because they're there for a
reason. So pay attention.
Yeah.
Do you think the C standard helps any
other programming languages?
Yes, a lot. Basically C is not only a
programming language. is also somehow a
lingua franka how to approach how to
talk between different languages. So
basically all languages that you see
today at at some level they interface to
see and then some of the work is done at
C. Yeah, that's what I think about like
I was saying, I'm doing a lot of Rust
work at the moment and I'm seeing more
and more libraries be written in Rust
and then they expose a C interface and
every other language then uses that
interface to use that library
and often it goes the other way around.
So for example for Python once you do
want to do things efficiently and fast
people create some C library which they
interface from Python. So
yeah and then that means everyone else
can get it because it's written in C.
Yeah. Yeah, it's written in C and then
easy to use in Python. So these are
these compromises which are done today.
Should someone learn C today that's
never programmed before?
Yes, sure. Certainly. It's really one of
the programming languages. It's always
among the one first, second or third
used programming languages in the world.
So
I suppose for me I kind of think of it
like learning to speak English. You know
everything speaks C. you'll get by if
you can
translate ideas and things from C and
you can always understand what's under
the hood if you can
yeah yeah
I don't know where you hang out you know
can people follow you somewhere or how
can they get in touch if they've got
some questions
I'm on master so you would easily find
me there yeah also LinkedIn but I'm not
very active so basically it's mastered
on nowadays I try not to go on too much
on these commercial platforms
Thank you for coming on the show. It was
just as much fun as 5 years ago, more
so. So, thanks for coming back. This is
Gavin Henry for Software Engineering
Radio. Thank you for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
Ile Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Common
License 2.5. Thanks for listening.